<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><ANNEX xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.50-20130101.xd"><BIB.INSTANCE><DOCUMENT.REF FILE="L_2013347EN.01032001.doc.xml"><COLL>L</COLL><NO.OJ>347</NO.OJ><YEAR>2013</YEAR><LG.OJ>EN</LG.OJ><PAGE.FIRST>320</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><VOLUME.REF>01</VOLUME.REF></DOCUMENT.REF><DATE ISO="20131217">20131217</DATE><LG.DOC>EN</LG.DOC><NO.SEQ>0019.0012</NO.SEQ><PAGE.FIRST>457</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><PAGE.LAST>460</PAGE.LAST><PAGE.TOTAL>4</PAGE.TOTAL></BIB.INSTANCE><TITLE><TI><P>ANNEX XII</P></TI></TITLE><CONTENTS><GR.SEQ LEVEL="1"><TITLE><TI><P><HT TYPE="BOLD">INFORMATION AND COMMUNICATION ON SUPPORT FROM THE FUNDS</HT></P></TI></TITLE><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>LIST OF OPERATIONS</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>The list of operations referred to in Article 115(2) shall contain, in at least one of the official languages of the Member State, the following data fields:</P><LIST TYPE="DASH"><ITEM><P>beneficiary name (only of legal entities; no natural persons shall be named);</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>operation name;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>operation summary;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>operation start date;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>operation end date (expected date for physical completion or full implementation of the operation);</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>total eligible expenditure allocated to the operation;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>Union co-financing rate, as per priority axis;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>operation postcode; or other appropriate location indicator;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>country;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>name of category of intervention for the operation in accordance with point (b) (vi) of the first subparagraph of Article 96(2);</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>date of last update of the list of operations.</P></ITEM></LIST><P>The headings of the data fields shall be also provided in at least one other official language of the Union.</P></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>INFORMATION AND COMMUNICATION MEASURES FOR THE PUBLIC</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>The Member State, the managing authority and the beneficiaries shall take the steps necessary to provide information to, and communicate with, the public on operations supported by an operational programme in accordance with this Regulation.</P><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>2.1.</NO.P><TXT>Responsibilities of the Member State and the managing authority</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>The Member State and the managing authority shall ensure that the information and communication measures are implemented in accordance with the communication strategy and that those measures aim for the widest possible media coverage using various forms and methods of communication at the appropriate level.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>The Member State or the managing authority shall be responsible for at least the following information and communication measures:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>organising a major information activity publicising the launch of the operational programme or programmes, even prior to the approval of the relevant communication strategies;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>organising one major information activity a year which promotes the funding opportunities and the strategies pursued and presents the achievements of the operational programme or programmes, including, where relevant, major projects, joint action plans and other project examples;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(c)</NO.P><TXT>displaying the Union emblem at the premises of each managing authority;</TXT></NP></ITEM><?PAGE NO='458'?><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(d)</NO.P><TXT>publishing electronically the list of operations in accordance with Section 1 of this Annex;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(e)</NO.P><TXT>giving examples of operations, by operational programme, on the single website or on the operational programme's website that is accessible through the single website portal; the examples should be in a widely spoken official language of the Union other than the official language or languages of the Member State concerned;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(f)</NO.P><TXT>updating information about the operational programme's implementation, including, when appropriate, its main achievements, on the single website or on the operational programme's website that is accessible through the single website portal.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></P></NP><NP><NO.P>3.</NO.P><TXT>The managing authority shall involve in information and communication measures, in accordance with national laws and practices, the following bodies where appropriate:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>the partners referred to in Article 5;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>information centres on Europe, as well as Commission representation offices, and information offices of the European Parliament in the Member States;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(c)</NO.P><TXT>educational and research institutions.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></P><P>These bodies shall widely disseminate the information described in Article 115(1).</P></NP></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>2.2.</NO.P><TXT>Responsibilities of the beneficiaries</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>All information and communication measures provided by the beneficiary shall acknowledge support from the Funds to the operation by displaying:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>the Union emblem in accordance with the technical characteristics laid down in the implementing act adopted by the Commission under Article 115(4), together with a reference to the Union;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>a reference to the Fund or Funds supporting the operation.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></P><P>Where an information or communication measure relates to an operation or to several operations co-financed by more than one Fund, the reference provided for in point (b) may be replaced by a reference to the ESI Funds.</P></NP><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>During implementation of an operation, the beneficiary shall inform the public about the support obtained from the Funds by:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>providing on the beneficiary's website, where such a website exists, a short description of the operation, proportionate to the level of support, including its aims and results, and highlighting the financial support from the Union;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>placing, for operations not falling under points 4 and 5, at least one poster with information about the project (minimum size A3), including the financial support from the Union, at a location readily visible to the public, such as the entrance area of a building.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></P></NP><NP><NO.P>3.</NO.P><TXT>For operations supported by the ESF, and in appropriate cases for operations supported by the ERDF or Cohesion Fund, the beneficiary shall ensure that those taking part in an operation have been informed of this funding.</TXT><P>Any document, relating to the implementation of an operation which is used for the public or for participants, including any attendance or other certificate, shall include a statement to the effect that the operational programme was supported by the Fund or Funds.</P></NP><NP><NO.P>4.</NO.P><TXT>During implementation of an ERDF or Cohesion Fund operation, the beneficiary shall put up, at a location readily visible to the public, a temporary billboard of a significant size for each operation consisting of the financing of infrastructure or construction operations for which the total public support to the operation exceeds EUR <FT TYPE="NUMBER">500000</FT>.</TXT></NP><?PAGE NO='459'?><NP><NO.P>5.</NO.P><TXT>No later than three months after completion of an operation, the beneficiary shall put up a permanent plaque or billboard of significant size at a location readily visible to the public for each operation that fulfils the following criteria:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>the total public support to the operation exceeds EUR <FT TYPE="NUMBER">500000</FT>;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>the operation consists of the purchase of a physical object or of the financing of infrastructure or of construction operations.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></P><P>The plaque or billboard shall state the name and the main objective of the operation. It shall be prepared in accordance with the technical characteristics adopted by the Commission in accordance with Article 115(4).</P></NP></GR.SEQ></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>3.</NO.P><TXT>INFORMATION MEASURES FOR POTENTIAL BENEFICIARIES AND BENEFICIARIES</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>3.1.</NO.P><TXT>Information measures for potential beneficiaries</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>The managing authority shall ensure, in accordance with the communication strategy, that the operational programme's strategy and objectives, and the funding opportunities offered through joint support from the Union and the Member State, are disseminated widely to potential beneficiaries and all interested parties, with details of the financial support from the Funds concerned.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>The managing authority shall ensure that potential beneficiaries have access to the relevant information, including updated information where necessary, and taking into account the accessibility of electronic or other communication services for certain potential beneficiaries, on at least the following:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>the funding opportunities and the launching of application calls;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>the eligibility of expenditure conditions to be met in order to qualify for support under an operational programme;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(c)</NO.P><TXT>a description of the procedures for examining applications for funding and of the time periods involved;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(d)</NO.P><TXT>the criteria for selecting the operations to be supported;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(e)</NO.P><TXT>the contacts at national, regional or local level that are able to provide information on the operational programmes;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(f)</NO.P><TXT>the responsibility of potential beneficiaries to inform the public about the aim of the operation and the support from the Funds to the operation in accordance with point 2.2. The managing authority may request potential beneficiaries to propose indicative communication activities, proportional to the size of the operation, in the applications.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></P></NP></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>3.2.</NO.P><TXT>Information measures for beneficiaries</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>The managing authority shall inform beneficiaries that acceptance of funding constitutes an acceptance of their inclusion in the list of operations published in accordance with Article 115(2).</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>The managing authority shall provide information and communication tools, including templates in electronic format, to help beneficiaries to meet their obligations set out in point 2.2, where appropriate.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>4.</NO.P><TXT>ELEMENTS OF THE COMMUNICATION STRATEGY</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>The communication strategy drawn up by the managing authority and, where appropriate, by the Member State shall include the following elements:</P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>a description of the approach taken, including the main information and communication measures to be taken by the Member State or the managing authority and aimed at potential beneficiaries, beneficiaries, multipliers and the wider public, having regard to the aims described in Article 115;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>a description of materials that will be made available in formats accessible for people with disabilities;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(c)</NO.P><TXT>a description of how beneficiaries will be supported in their communication activities;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(d)</NO.P><TXT>the indicative budget for implementation of the strategy;</TXT></NP></ITEM><?PAGE NO='460'?><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(e)</NO.P><TXT>a description of the administrative bodies, including the staff resources, responsible for implementing the information and communication measures;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(f)</NO.P><TXT>the arrangements for the information and communication measures referred to in point 2, including the website or website portal at which such data may be found;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(g)</NO.P><TXT>an indication of how the information and communication measures shall be assessed in terms of visibility and awareness of policy, operational programmes and operations, and of the role played by the Funds and the Union;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(h)</NO.P><TXT>where appropriate, a description of the use of the main results of the previous operational programme;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(i)</NO.P><TXT>an annual update setting out the information and communication activities to be carried out in the following year.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></GR.SEQ></GR.SEQ></CONTENTS></ANNEX>
