<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><ANNEX xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.50-20130101.xd"><BIB.INSTANCE><DOCUMENT.REF FILE="L_2013347EN.01032001.doc.xml"><COLL>L</COLL><NO.OJ>347</NO.OJ><YEAR>2013</YEAR><LG.OJ>EN</LG.OJ><PAGE.FIRST>320</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><VOLUME.REF>01</VOLUME.REF></DOCUMENT.REF><DATE ISO="20131217">20131217</DATE><LG.DOC>EN</LG.DOC><NO.SEQ>0019.0010</NO.SEQ><PAGE.FIRST>436</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><PAGE.LAST>437</PAGE.LAST><PAGE.TOTAL>2</PAGE.TOTAL></BIB.INSTANCE><TITLE><TI><P>ANNEX X</P></TI></TITLE><CONTENTS><GR.SEQ LEVEL="1"><TITLE><TI><P><HT TYPE="BOLD">ADDITIONALITY</HT></P></TI></TITLE><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>PUBLIC OR EQUIVALENT STRUCTURAL EXPENDITURE</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>In Member States in which less developed regions cover at least 65 % of the population, the figure on gross fixed capital formation reported in the Stability and Convergence Programmes, prepared by Member States in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1466/97 to present their medium term budgetary strategy, will be used to determine public or equivalent structural expenditure. The figure to be used shall be that reported in the context of the general government balance and debt and related to general government budgetary prospects and shall be presented as a percentage of GDP.</P><P>In those Member States in which less developed regions cover more than 15 % and less than 65 % of the population, the total figure on gross fixed capital formation in the less developed regions will be used to determine public or equivalent structural expenditure. It shall be reported in the same format as laid down in the first subparagraph.</P></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>VERIFICATION</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>Verifications of additionality in accordance with Article 95(5) are subject to the following rules:</P><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>2.1</NO.P><TXT>Ex ante verification</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>When a Member State submits a Partnership Agreement, it shall provide information on the planned profile of expenditure in the format of Table 1.</TXT><P><TBL COLS="8" NO.SEQ="0001"><TITLE><TI><P>Table 1</P></TI></TITLE><CORPUS><ROW TYPE="HEADER"><CELL COL="1" TYPE="HEADER">Expenditure of the General Government as a share of GDP</CELL><CELL COL="2" TYPE="HEADER">2014</CELL><CELL COL="3" TYPE="HEADER">2015</CELL><CELL COL="4" TYPE="HEADER">2016</CELL><CELL COL="5" TYPE="HEADER">2017</CELL><CELL COL="6" TYPE="HEADER">2018</CELL><CELL COL="7" TYPE="HEADER">2019</CELL><CELL COL="8" TYPE="HEADER">2020</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL COL="1">P51</CELL><CELL COL="2">X</CELL><CELL COL="3">X</CELL><CELL COL="4">X</CELL><CELL COL="5">X</CELL><CELL COL="6">X</CELL><CELL COL="7">X</CELL><CELL COL="8">X</CELL></ROW></CORPUS></TBL></P></NP><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>Member States, in which less developed regions cover more than 15 % and less than 65 % of the population, shall also provide information on the planned profile of expenditure in those less developed regions in the format of Table 2.</TXT><P><TBL COLS="8" NO.SEQ="0002"><TITLE><TI><P>Table 2</P></TI></TITLE><CORPUS><ROW TYPE="HEADER"><CELL COL="1" TYPE="HEADER"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="2" TYPE="HEADER">2014</CELL><CELL COL="3" TYPE="HEADER">2015</CELL><CELL COL="4" TYPE="HEADER">2016</CELL><CELL COL="5" TYPE="HEADER">2017</CELL><CELL COL="6" TYPE="HEADER">2018</CELL><CELL COL="7" TYPE="HEADER">2019</CELL><CELL COL="8" TYPE="HEADER">2020</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL COL="1" TYPE="HEADER">Gross Fixed Capital Formation of the General Government in the less developed regions as a share of GDP</CELL><CELL COL="2">X</CELL><CELL COL="3">X</CELL><CELL COL="4">X</CELL><CELL COL="5">X</CELL><CELL COL="6">X</CELL><CELL COL="7">X</CELL><CELL COL="8">X</CELL></ROW></CORPUS></TBL></P></NP><NP><NO.P>(c)</NO.P><TXT>Member States shall provide to the Commission information on the main macroeconomic indicators and forecasts underlying the level of public or equivalent structural expenditure.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(d)</NO.P><TXT>Member States, in which less developed regions cover more than 15 % and less than 65 % of the population, shall also provide to the Commission information on the method used to estimate gross fixed capital formation in those regions. For this purpose, Member States shall use regional level public investment data where available. In the event that such data is not available, or in other duly justified cases, including where a Member State for the period 2014-2020 has significantly changed the regional breakdown as defined in Regulation (EC) No 1059/2003, gross fixed capital formation can be estimated by applying regional public expenditure indicators or regional population to national level public investment data.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(e)</NO.P><TXT>Once there is agreement by the Commission and the Member State, Table 1 and, where applicable, Table 2 will be included in the Partnership Agreement of the Member State concerned as the reference level of the public or equivalent structural expenditure to be maintained in the years 2014-2020.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ><?PAGE NO='437'?><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>2.2</NO.P><TXT>Mid-term verification</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>At the time of the mid-term verification, a Member State shall be deemed to have maintained the level of public or equivalent structural expenditure if the annual average of expenditure in the years 2014-2017 is equal to or higher than the reference level of expenditure set in the Partnership Agreement.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>Following the mid-term verification, the Commission may revise, in consultation with a Member State, the reference level of public or equivalent structural expenditure in the Partnership Agreement if the economic situation of the Member State has significantly changed from that estimated at the time of adoption of the Partnership Agreement.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>2.3</NO.P><TXT>Ex post verification</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>At the time of the ex post verification, a Member State shall be deemed to have maintained the level of public or equivalent structural expenditure if the annual average of expenditure in the years 2014-2020 is equal to or higher than the reference level of expenditure set in the Partnership Agreement.</P></GR.SEQ></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>3.</NO.P><TXT>FINANCIAL CORRECTION RATES FOLLOWING EX POST VERIFICATION</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>Where the Commission decides to carry out a financial correction in accordance with Article 95(6), the rate of financial correction shall be obtained by subtracting 3 % from the difference between the reference level in the Partnership Agreement and the level achieved, expressed as a percentage of the reference level, and then dividing the result by 10. The financial correction shall be determined by applying that rate of financial correction to the Funds' contribution to the Member State concerned for the less developed regions for the full programming period.</P><P>If the difference between the reference level in the Partnership Agreement and the level achieved, expressed as a percentage of the reference level in the Partnership Agreement, is 3 % or less, no financial correction shall be made.</P><P>The financial correction shall not exceed 5 % of the Funds' allocation to the Member State concerned for the less developed regions for the full programming period.</P></GR.SEQ></GR.SEQ></CONTENTS></ANNEX>
