<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><ANNEX xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.50-20130101.xd"><BIB.INSTANCE><DOCUMENT.REF FILE="L_2013347EN.01032001.doc.xml"><COLL>L</COLL><NO.OJ>347</NO.OJ><YEAR>2013</YEAR><LG.OJ>EN</LG.OJ><PAGE.FIRST>320</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><VOLUME.REF>01</VOLUME.REF></DOCUMENT.REF><DATE ISO="20131217">20131217</DATE><LG.DOC>EN</LG.DOC><NO.SEQ>0019.0008</NO.SEQ><PAGE.FIRST>434</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><PAGE.LAST>434</PAGE.LAST><PAGE.TOTAL>1</PAGE.TOTAL></BIB.INSTANCE><TITLE><TI><P>ANNEX VIII</P></TI></TITLE><CONTENTS><GR.SEQ LEVEL="1"><TITLE><TI><P><HT TYPE="BOLD">METHODOLOGY CONCERNING THE SPECIFIC ALLOCATION FOR THE YEI REFERRED TO IN ARTICLE 91</HT></P></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>I.</NO.P><TXT>The breakdown of the specific allocation for the YEI shall be determined in accordance with the following steps:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="ARAB"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>The number of young unemployed persons between the ages of 15-24 shall be identified in the eligible NUTS level 2 regions as defined in Article 16 of the ESF Regulation, namely NUTS level 2 regions that have youth unemployment rates for young persons aged 15 to 24 of more than 25 % in 2012 and, for Member States where the youth unemployment rate has increased by more than 30 % in 2012, regions that have youth unemployment rates of more than 20 % in 2012 (the <QUOT.START ID="QS0001" REF.END="QE0001" CODE="2018"/>eligible regions<QUOT.END ID="QE0001" REF.START="QS0001" CODE="2019"/>).</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>The allocation corresponding to each eligible region shall be calculated on the basis of the ratio between the number of young unemployed persons in the eligible region and the total number of young unemployed persons referred to in point 1 in all eligible regions.</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>3.</NO.P><TXT>The allocation for each Member State shall be the sum of the allocations for each of its eligible regions.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></P></NP><NP><NO.P>II.</NO.P><TXT>The specific allocation for the YEI shall not be taken into account for the purpose of applying the capping rules set out in Annex VII in relation to the allocation of the global resources.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>III.</NO.P><TXT>For the determination of the specific allocation from the YEI to Mayotte, the youth unemployment rate and number of young unemployed persons shall be determined on the basis of the latest available data at national level as long as Eurostat data at NUTS level 2 are not available.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>IV.</NO.P><TXT>The resources for the YEI may be revised upwards for the years 2016 to 2020 in the framework of the budgetary procedure in accordance with Article 14 of Regulation (UE, Euratom) No 1311/2013. The breakdown by Member State of the additional resources shall follow the same steps as applied for the initial allocation but shall refer to the latest available annual data.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ></CONTENTS></ANNEX>
