<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><ANNEX xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.50-20130101.xd"><BIB.INSTANCE><DOCUMENT.REF FILE="L_2013347EN.01032001.doc.xml"><COLL>L</COLL><NO.OJ>347</NO.OJ><YEAR>2013</YEAR><LG.OJ>EN</LG.OJ><PAGE.FIRST>320</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><VOLUME.REF>01</VOLUME.REF></DOCUMENT.REF><DATE ISO="20131217">20131217</DATE><LG.DOC>EN</LG.DOC><NO.SEQ>0019.0002</NO.SEQ><PAGE.FIRST>423</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><PAGE.LAST>423</PAGE.LAST><PAGE.TOTAL>1</PAGE.TOTAL></BIB.INSTANCE><TITLE><TI><P>ANNEX II</P></TI></TITLE><CONTENTS><GR.SEQ LEVEL="1"><TITLE><TI><P><HT TYPE="BOLD">METHOD FOR ESTABLISHING THE PERFORMANCE FRAMEWORK</HT></P></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>The performance framework shall consist of milestones established for each priority, with the exception of priorities dedicated to technical assistance and programmes dedicated to financial instruments in accordance with Article 39, for the year 2018 and targets established for 2023. The milestones and targets shall be presented in accordance with the format set out in table 1.</TXT><P><TBL COLS="5" NO.SEQ="0001"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>Table 1:</NO.P><TXT>Standard format for the performance framework</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><CORPUS><ROW TYPE="HEADER"><CELL COL="1" TYPE="HEADER">Priority</CELL><CELL COL="2" TYPE="HEADER">Indicator and measurement unit, where appropriate</CELL><CELL COL="3" TYPE="HEADER"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="4" TYPE="HEADER">Milestone for 2018</CELL><CELL COL="5" TYPE="HEADER">Target for 2023</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL COL="1"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="2"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="3"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="4"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="5"><IE/></CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL COL="1"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="2"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="3"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="4"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="5"><IE/></CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL COL="1"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="2"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="3"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="4"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="5"><IE/></CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL COL="1"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="2"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="3"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="4"><IE/></CELL><CELL COL="5"><IE/></CELL></ROW></CORPUS></TBL></P></NP><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>Milestones are intermediate targets, directly linked to the achievement of the specific objective of a priority, where appropriate, expressing the intended progress towards the targets set for the end of the period. Milestones established for 2018 shall include financial indicators, output indicators and, where appropriate result indicators, which are closely linked to the supported policy interventions. Result indicators shall not be taken into account for the purposes of Article 22(6) and (7). Milestones may also be established for key implementation steps.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>3.</NO.P><TXT>Milestones and targets shall be:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>realistic, achievable, relevant, capturing essential information on the progress of a priority;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>consistent with the nature and character of the specific objectives of the priority;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(c)</NO.P><TXT>transparent, with objectively verifiable targets and the source data identified and, where possible, publicly available;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(d)</NO.P><TXT>verifiable, without imposing a disproportionate administrative burden;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(e)</NO.P><TXT>consistent across programmes, where appropriate.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></P></NP><NP><NO.P>4.</NO.P><TXT>The targets for 2023 for a given priority shall be established taking into account the amount of performance reserve related to the priority.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>5.</NO.P><TXT>In duly justified cases, such as a significant change in the economic, environmental and labour market conditions in a Member State or region, and in addition to amendments resulting from changes in allocations for a given priority, that Member State may propose the revision of milestones and targets in accordance with Article 30.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ></CONTENTS></ANNEX>
