<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><ANNEX xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.50-20130101.xd"><BIB.INSTANCE><DOCUMENT.REF FILE="L_2013347EN.01032001.doc.xml"><COLL>L</COLL><NO.OJ>347</NO.OJ><YEAR>2013</YEAR><LG.OJ>EN</LG.OJ><PAGE.FIRST>320</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><VOLUME.REF>01</VOLUME.REF></DOCUMENT.REF><DATE ISO="20131217">20131217</DATE><LG.DOC>EN</LG.DOC><NO.SEQ>0019.0013</NO.SEQ><PAGE.FIRST>461</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><PAGE.LAST>462</PAGE.LAST><PAGE.TOTAL>2</PAGE.TOTAL></BIB.INSTANCE><TITLE><TI><P>ANNEX XIII</P></TI></TITLE><CONTENTS><GR.SEQ LEVEL="1"><TITLE><TI><P><HT TYPE="BOLD">DESIGNATION CRITERIA FOR THE MANAGING AUTHORITY AND THE CERTIFYING AUTHORITY</HT></P></TI></TITLE><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>1.</NO.P><TXT>INTERNAL CONTROL ENVIRONMENT</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>(i)</NO.P><TXT>Existence of an organisational structure covering the functions of managing and certifying authorities and the allocation of functions within each of those authorities, ensuring that the principle of separation of functions, where appropriate, is respected.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(ii)</NO.P><TXT>Framework for ensuring, in the event of delegation of tasks to intermediate bodies, the definition of their respective responsibilities and obligations, the verification of their capacities to carry out delegated tasks and the existence of reporting procedures.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(iii)</NO.P><TXT>Reporting and monitoring procedures for irregularities and for the recovery of amounts unduly paid.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(iv)</NO.P><TXT>Plan for allocation of appropriate human resources with necessary technical skills, at different levels and for different functions in the organisation.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>2.</NO.P><TXT>RISK MANAGEMENT</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>Taking into account the principle of proportionality, a framework for ensuring that an appropriate risk management exercise is conducted when necessary, and in particular, in the event of major modifications to the activities.</P></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>3.</NO.P><TXT>MANAGEMENT AND CONTROL ACTIVITIES</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>A.</NO.P><TXT>Managing authority</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>(i)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures regarding grant applications, appraisal of applications, selection for funding, including instructions and guidance ensuring the contribution of operations, in accordance with point (a)(i) of Article 125(3), to achieving the specific objectives and results of the relevant priority.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(ii)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures for management verifications including administrative verifications in respect of each application for reimbursement by beneficiaries and the on-the-spot verifications of operations.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(iii)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures for treatment of applications for reimbursement by beneficiaries and authorisation of payments.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(iv)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures for a system to collect, record and store in computerised form data on each operation, including, where appropriate, data on individual participants and a breakdown of data on indicators by gender where required, and to ensure that systems security is in line with internationally accepted standards.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(v)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures established by the managing authority to ensure that beneficiaries maintain either a separate accounting system or an adequate accounting code for all transactions relating to an operation.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(vi)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures for putting in place effective and proportionate anti-fraud measures.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(vii)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures to ensure an adequate audit trail and archiving system.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(viii)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures to draw up the management declaration of assurance, report on the controls carried out and weaknesses identified, and the annual summary of final audits and controls.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(ix)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures to ensure the provision to the beneficiary of a document setting out the conditions for support for each operation.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ><?PAGE NO='462'?><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>B.</NO.P><TXT>Certifying authority</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>(i)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures for certifying interim payment applications to the Commission.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(ii)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures for drawing up the accounts and certifying that they are true, complete and accurate and that the expenditure complies with applicable law taking into account the results of all audits.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(iii)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures for ensuring an adequate audit trail by maintaining accounting records including amounts recoverable, recovered and withdrawn for each operation, in computerised form.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(iv)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures, where appropriate, to ensure that the certifying authority receives adequate information from the managing authority on the verifications carried out, and the results of the audits carried out by or under the responsibility of the audit authority.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="2"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>4.</NO.P><TXT>MONITORING</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>A.</NO.P><TXT>Managing authority</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><NP><NO.P>(i)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures to support the work of the monitoring committee.</TXT></NP><NP><NO.P>(ii)</NO.P><TXT>Procedures to draw up and submit to the Commission annual and final implementation reports.</TXT></NP></GR.SEQ><GR.SEQ LEVEL="3"><TITLE><TI><NP><NO.P>B.</NO.P><TXT>Certifying authority</TXT></NP></TI></TITLE><P>Procedures on the fulfilment of the responsibilities of the certifying authority for monitoring the results of the management verifications and the results of the audits carried out by or under the responsibility of the audit authority before submitting payment applications to the Commission.</P></GR.SEQ></GR.SEQ></GR.SEQ></CONTENTS></ANNEX>
